Gary, you're in a different spot.
I mean, just slightly, but good morning, everyone.
You know, you give the worship team one little pep talk about how schedules don't matter.
What matters is us spending time in the presence of the Lord.
And now I have 20 minutes to preach a 45-minute sermon.
So here we are.
It's, you know, but what we did this morning was we applied the sermon that I'm about to preach.
Because what we're going to find out, and hopefully a condensed amount of time, is that joy is linked to the presence of God.
And so excited that we kind of already got started on the right foot.
We are in a series on the names of God, and today we are rounding the corner into week four of our Advent series.
Week one, Kent went over the name of God, Yahweh, and he kind of shared that the entire Bible is about a knowable God stretching out his hand towards you in relationship.
We moved on to Wonderful Counselor, that this name of God teaches us and demonstrates to us how we should live.
And because of that, we can have hope in his wisdom and his counsel, because it will always lead to abundant life.
Last week, we talked about God as everlasting Father who is filled with love towards his children.
And today, we're actually going to pivot from the Isaiah 9 passage and look at the title of Emmanuel, God with us.
So, let's pray.
Father, we love you, and we do just thank you for this extended time in your presence.
We are in a holiday season that is consumer-driven, fast-paced, and often really just distracts us from the whole point of the season,
which is to really just spend four weeks anticipating and preparing to celebrate your first coming as we await your second.
God, that the whole Scripture is about you being knowable and relational.
And God, I pray that today would be just another reminder for us to slow down, to keep our eyes open, to be available to your presence in the midst of the busyness and consumeristic nature of the holiday season.
God, just anchor our hearts in your presence for your glory.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
Well, I don't know about you, but with the change of seasons has come an uptick in my trips to my storage shed.
This is an actual tub from my storage shed.
We've been taking out summer clothes, bringing in winter clothes, taking out fall decorations, bringing in Christmas decorations.
And what I have become increasingly aware of over the past few weeks is that the labels on my storage bins are practically useless.
Anybody else, or am I the only one?
Now, I do want to make a distinction that there are storage bins that my wife is in charge of.
Those are labeled correctly, and what is on the lid is inside the bin.
But any bin that I have had my hands on in the past few years often has, like, three different things written on it.
Some are scratched out, some are scratched out partially.
And what's really interesting is when you open it up, and it's actually something that is in none of the three labels on the tub.
And I actually, I found my hunting clothes the other day in the tub labeled fall decor.
Which, if you know my track record for hunting, it kind of is fall decor, because in order for them to be hunting clothes, I would have to come home with a deer.
And so, you know, here we are.
But it makes finding what I'm looking for very difficult.
And the past few weeks, as I have kind of been on a rabbit trail, and I've got to admit to you up front that I need you guys to do your best to follow along with me, because I have been on a rabbit trail in study.
And this message is a result of that rabbit trail.
And by the end of it, you can tell that it's a rabbit trail, which I usually try and consolidate, organize, and present to you a much more polished version.
But I'm not, we're on a rabbit trail together, okay?
So I need you to focus with me.
But as I've been on this rabbit trail, I've realized that I think joy is one of these biblical words where oftentimes we have containers, we have this container of joy.
And we've got a few different labels on the top, sermons that we've heard about joy, some, like, working definitions of what joy is.
And I have this myself.
I've preached on joy many times in the past.
And yet this week, these actually past three weeks, as I've been on this rabbit trail, I'm starting to open up this tub and realize that what's inside the biblical idea of joy is actually a little bit different and more robust and actually kind of slightly disconnected from the label that I have on the lid.
Does that make sense?
And so what I want to do this morning is, and maybe you guys nailed it, maybe you guys know your label for joy is perfect and I'm learning new things.
But what I want to do is help you kind of follow this rabbit trail that I've been on that has given me a more clear understanding of what biblical joy is.
Because I think the more we understand what it is, the better we can walk in it, experience it in real and meaningful ways.
And so my goal today is going to be for you to consider me your Marie Kondo.
Anybody?
I knew that joke was going to land for like 12 people, but I wanted to do it anyway.
So we're going to tidy up our definition of joy this morning.
I'm so proud of myself for that one.
All right.
Just ask your neighbor that laughed and it'll be fine.
So a little bit of backstory before we really chase down the rabbit trail.
A few weeks ago, I leaned into this topic of psychology called attachment theory.
And as I kind of went down this rabbit hole, I got to acknowledge that Marissa has been on the same rabbit hole, rabbit trail.
Why do I keep saying rabbit hole?
All right.
Rabbit trail.
Are we good?
I feel like I'm going to pass out.
All right.
Marissa, my wife has been on this rabbit trail for like a year prior to this, but we'd never had any conversations about it.
And so I come home and I'm like, this thing I learned.
And she's like, oh yeah, well, here's seven other things that I learned about that same thing.
And I was like, okay, that's my sermon.
And so I've been following a rabbit trail that Marissa has been on for about a year.
So I want to give her some credit for that.
But I leaned into this topic of attachment theory.
It's a psychology idea.
And I actually started leaning into it when I was studying the title of Everlasting Father.
Because attachment theory is all about how your kind of first years of life, what was your relationship like with your primary caregiver?
And how that actually forms kind of neurological pathways in our brain that actually affect how we do relationships for the rest of our lives.
And so any of you who have been in therapy have probably interacted with some of these topics before.
But I was like, man, what is it?
What might our formative years with our primary caregivers, how might that impact the way that we think about God as Everlasting Father?
And so I was on this kind of journey trying to figure out how that might work into my sermon last week on love and Everlasting Father.
And it turned out that joy just kept coming up over and over and over again in this idea of attachment theory.
And I was like, huh, I don't, those seem disconnected to me.
So then as I was studying attachment theory, that led me into the field of neuroscience, which I have no business being in the field of neuroscience.
But as I interacted with some neuroscience ideas, it just kept coming up, this topic of joy being connected to your relationship with your primary caregiver.
And the illustration they use is like when you watch a parent interact with their baby.
And making eye contact, this facial connection, and the baby begins to smile, and the mom or the dad begins to smile.
And there's this mutual reciprocal joy that is rooted in a relationship of delight.
And the neuroscientists actually call this kind of like this, they label it as this joy section of your brain that begins to develop before you even learn language.
It's literally based on this face-to-face relationship with your primary caregiver.
Jacques Poncep, who is the father of effective neuroscience, I know you guys all are familiar with him.
He labeled the brain into seven primary emotional systems, and one of those is joy.
It's this idea of this face-to-face interaction of mutual kind of delight and relationship.
And so as I got down this rabbit trail further and further, I came across this neuroscientist who defined joy ultimately in the idea of safe and secure relationships.
And I don't know about you, but that like is definitely sideways from what I think about when I think about joy.
It's not really what I have on the top of the label on my joy container.
And so I was like, hmm, I'm a little bit skeptical, but I kept chasing this rabbit trail down.
And I found one neuroscientist say this way, joy emerges when the nervous system detects safety in another's face and voice.
And I was like, again, not really what I think about when I think about joy.
I've preached on joy in the past, and this doesn't really look like anything, any one of my previous working definitions.
So I was a little bit skeptical.
And so I went from attachment theory to neuroscience, back to attachment theory.
You guys following with me?
I know it's hard.
I promise I will make it make sense, at least in my brain.
I went back to attachment theory, but this time with some Christian, with a Christian neuroscientist and psychiatrist who specialize in attachment theory.
And this is their definition of joy.
These are Christians who know the Bible, theologians.
They say joy is the experience of being with someone who is glad to be with you.
And apparently some of you have already known this for a long time.
I'm so thankful that I'm learning new things with you in front of you.
But again, like I read this definition.
I'm like, this is really good, but it's not how I would have defined joy previously.
And so at this point, chasing the rabbit trail, both secular and Christian psychologists and neuroscientists were all saying very similar things about joy.
That looked a lot different than my working definition.
So I did what any good pastor would do.
I did a word study on joy in the Scriptures.
And I was immediately blown away by the amount of times there is a clear and obvious connection between joy and face-to-face presence in safe relationships in the Scriptures.
A couple examples here.
Psalm chapter 16, verse 11.
And I could have done a 40-minute section in my sermon just on examples.
So like we're just going to fly through these.
Psalm 16, verse 11.
You make known to me the path of life.
You will fill me with joy in your presence, with eternal pleasures at your right hand.
Psalm 21, 6.
Surely you have granted him unending blessings and made him glad with the joy of your presence.
John 15, which is Jesus' most famous talk about abiding in the presence of God, in like presence relationship about the vine and the branch and abiding.
He says this in John 15.
If you keep my commandments, you will remain in my love, just as I have kept my Father's commandments and remain in his love.
I have told you this.
This idea of abiding, being in the presence of, in relationship with, I've told you this so that my joy may be in you and that your joy may be complete.
The last one that really blew me away, 2 John 1, or chapter 1, verse 12.
John writes to a church, an early church, and he says,
I have much to write to you, but I do not want to use paper and ink.
Instead, I hope to visit you and talk with you face to face so that our joy may be complete.
So when I began to put all of this together, it seems to me like there is a clear and accurate definition of biblical joy that emphasizes this priority on face to face relationships with mutual delight.
That there's security in relationship that leads to joy.
And I had never really made this direct connection that joy really required the presence of another person.
And typically, what we're going to get to, obviously, is that it requires the presence of God to have full, everlasting joy.
But I never really thought about the idea that joy was rooted in relationship.
Am I the only one that is learning new things today?
Okay, thank you.
That's good.
I was nervous because, you know, I don't know everything.
And then one scholar said it, put it this way.
They said, pleasure can be experienced alone, but joy always requires another person.
Pleasure.
These are similar emotions that oftentimes we get different emotions confused.
Complex emotions get blended together.
He says, pleasure can be experienced alone, but joy always requires another person.
Which leads me to our Scriptures for the day.
One was read to us by the flock hearts this morning in Luke chapter 2, verse 10, where the angel comes to the shepherds and says,
Do not be afraid, I bring you good news that will cause great joy for all people.
And the question then for me becomes, how can the birth of an oppressed and impoverished infant in the one-stop light town of the Podunk Hills of the Judean countryside 2,000 years ago,
possibly bring good news that will lead to great joy for all people.
Right?
This is what the angel is announcing.
The birth of this infant who is oppressed and impoverished in a podunk town in the middle of nowhere.
How can the birth of this one individual provide good news that will lead to great joy for all people?
It sounds like a ridiculous statement unless you understand that joy is the emotional response of a safe and secure relationship with mutual delight.
Which leads us to Matthew's account of the story when he quotes the prophet Isaiah saying,
The virgin will conceive and give birth to a son, and they will call him Emmanuel, which means God with us.
This is where we begin to make the connections work.
If our working definition of joy is correct, then true and everlasting joy is now available to each one of us
because this oppressed, impoverished infant in a one-stop light town in the Podunk Hills of the Judean countryside was born
and because that infant is not just an infant, but he is God in the flesh.
True and everlasting joy is now available to us because the everlasting Father who created us
and sustains us comes near to us.
Emmanuel means that God delights in you, and he is seeking out a face-to-face relationship of delight resulting in joy.
This is where joy comes from.
God loves you, that you are safe and secure and delighted, and the same way that you watch a mother
dote over their new infant baby, the Lord has come to dwell in our presence.
He has come for a face-to-face, safe, secure relationship of delight.
He delights in you so much so that he came to be with us and to die in our place.
This is what we were made for.
This is what our heart aches for.
Think about the early, the first pages of Scripture where you hear that the God who made us was walking in the cool of the garden,
looking for Adam and Eve.
We were created for this face-to-face relationship that produces ultimate joy, joy that can't be shaken,
and we have turned away from that relationship.
And therefore, we are all depleted in some way, shape, or form of the joy that we were made for.
And we all go searching for it in different places and in different ways.
And we can't find it apart from the everlasting Father, the Prince of Peace, Emmanuel, who is God with us.
My first point for this morning is that Emmanuel is the source of everlasting joy.
We read about, in the Scriptures, the triune nature of God, the God, the Father, God, the Son, and God, the Holy Spirit.
We're in relationship with one another before creation even began.
It is out of joy that they even create us.
They didn't need to create us.
They created us out of their joyful relationship with one another.
In his presence is fullness of joy.
We've disconnected from this secure relationship, and one of the consequences of that decision is we have depleted joy,
which wreaks all kinds of havoc in our lives and in our culture and the world around us.
We're searching for stability and connection in all the wrong places.
We feel like we're adrift to sea without an anchor.
Just look around our culture.
Think about your life.
We're all just little babies looking for someone to tell us that we're safe, that we're loved,
that it's going to be okay.
And this is the title of Emmanuel.
This is what it brings to us, that Jesus became God in the flesh to dwell among us,
to demonstrate to us that we are safe and secure and that everything's going to be okay
because the one who made us, who created us for relationship with him,
has come to restore that relationship with us.
This is the good news that leads to joy for all people.
Secondly, not only is he the source of everlasting joy, but he brings everlasting joy through his incarnational presence.
Jesus came as the face-to-face representative of God in the flesh.
Anyone who saw Jesus saw the Father.
And the incarnation, the birth of Jesus of God with us is the climax point of all human history.
He drew near to us who were far off and joy depleted.
Those of us who are damaging ourselves through broken and insecure relationships, overcome by the burdens of the world,
all to bring us good news that will result in great joy.
The God who made us is inviting us into an everlasting relationship, delight, and security.
When the neuroscientists talk about a child who has a safe and secure connection at an early age,
they talk about the implications of that person for the rest of their life.
They say, one, people who have secure attachments at an early age are usually emotionally healthy.
They have safe boundaries and just good relationships for the rest of their lives.
It's kind of a key marker of these people.
And second, they have resilience in the midst of difficulty.
It's because, like, when they cried as an infant, they had a parent come to them and fix the problem.
And so deep wired in their brain is this belief that, like, I'm going to be okay.
Even when things are hard, even when things are difficult, I'm going to be okay.
And this is what biblical joy is all about, that those of us who have established a relationship with God,
our Father, who loves us, who owns the cattle on a thousand hills,
when we are going through financial struggle, when we are going through health struggles,
when we are going through difficulty, when we are going through pain,
we can look up to our Father in heaven and be reminded that we are safe and secure and delighted
and because of the work of Jesus.
This brings resilience in the midst of difficulty.
This is why joy is an emotion that we can experience even when things are hard.
Because the God who made us loves us and came to bring joy to us through his incarnational presence.
We can experience joy in human relationships, but it's temporary joy because relationships are always temporary.
Everlasting joy can only be felt through a relationship with the everlasting one.
The incarnation of Jesus, it brings everlasting joy to us, and it is the climax of human history,
but it's just the beginning of God's plan for restoring great joy to all people.
Just before Jesus is going to go to the cross, he tells his disciples in one of their final lengthy discussions
that he's going to leave them.
And he says, I'm going to go away, and you're going to be filled with sorrow.
But then I'm going to return, and you're going to experience great joy, right?
Rooted in presence.
But what he says in this conversation is he says,
And this gives every follower of Jesus for the rest of human history direct access to a face-to-face relationship with God
through the indwelling presence of the Holy Spirit.
This is where our joy is rooted in, that the presence of God draws near to us through the Holy Spirit.
This is the good news that leads to great joy for all people,
is that if we will trust in Jesus, he will send his spirit to us,
and we can have interaction with, face-to-face presence with the God who made us.
My third point is that Emmanuel sends everlasting joy through his indwelling presence.
Jesus was God in the flesh for a small group of people in Israel in the first century.
But through his incarnation, we now all have access to him through the indwelling presence of his Holy Spirit.
We have direct access to the presence of God at all times, no matter what we're going through,
no matter what difficulties we might face, no matter what broken relationships come our way.
We can draw near to Emmanuel who has drawn near to us.
And this is where I really want to cash in on our trip down the rabbit trail.
It was a lot of work, a little bit confusing, probably not my clearest outline of all time,
but I think many of us are searching for joy and missing it because we have a misunderstanding of how to get it.
Joy is a relational emotion.
It is the neurological response to being in a safe and secure relationship of mutual delight.
Many of us are searching for joy in human relationships, broken human relationships.
Many of us are putting too much emphasis on getting joy from another person.
And that person will always let you down.
They will always fail you.
You will always fail them.
You are not going to be everything that they need to be,
and they are not going to be everything that you need to be.
The best human relationships will result in temporary joy.
And many of us are searching for joy, everlasting joy, the joy that we were created for,
and we're searching for it apart from God.
It's never going to happen.
We're always going to be joy depleted if we try and use other people in our relationships with others
to fill us with the joy that God, that only God can bring.
Some of us are doing it in good relationships, and that's why it works some,
because human beings in the image of God bring us delight and joy when there's healthy relationships.
Some of us are looking for it in unhealthy relationships.
Some of us don't know how to have healthy relationships,
and it goes back to our primary, our first relationship with our primary caregivers.
And the beautiful thing about God is that he created our brain in a way that it can create new memories
and be healed from our trauma as children.
That God literally created your brain so that the gospel, the good news of Jesus, can heal it.
So many of us are searching for joy in human relationships.
Others of us are trying to get it through digital relationships.
I mean, just think about the world we live in today.
For many of us, if we're talking about joy being face-to-face relational safety and security and mutual delight,
and like 95% of our face-to-face time with other people is through a screen,
it's no wonder that our joy is depleted,
because we're not interacting with real human beings.
We're not investing in people that are right in front of us.
We're too busy worried about what our 2,000 followers might think about our political opinion
rather than the three people that God asked you to invest in.
I mean, what is pornography if it isn't searching for what we're looking for in joy
and only getting temporary pleasure, screen time,
removing face-to-face investment in safe and secure relationships?
What is this brokenness that we've invited into our lives except for us searching for joy in all of the wrong places?
Pleasure can happen in isolation, but joy requires relationship.
Others of us are trying to experience joy through substances that alter the neurological state.
There's a reason we've talked about the brain today.
We can create some false experiences of pleasure with different chemicals that we put into our body.
But these are temporary and short-lived.
There's a reason the Scripture says,
don't be drunk with wine, but be filled with the Holy Spirit.
Right?
It's this similar, like the being drunk with wine can give us the joy of the being filled with the Holy Spirit temporarily.
But ultimately, it leads us down a path of destruction when being filled with the Holy Spirit leads us down a path that leads to abundant life.
So my kind of land the plain statement for this whole rabbit trail that you guys have been so gracious to come down with me,
I appreciate you all, is this.
Joy is the primary emotional response of the gospel made possible through the incarnational and indwelling presence of Emmanuel, God with us.
Joy is the primary emotional response of being in a safe, secure, face-to-face relationship with someone who delights in you.
What is the gospel if it is not God, Emmanuel, coming down in the flesh and being face-to-face?
Face-to-face with us.
Telling us he loves us, that we're forgiven, and that everything we need is ultimately going to be redeemed through the victory that Jesus had in his resurrection.
Kelly, you can come up.
So if I've persuaded you at all that this is even a decent relabeling of our joy tub,
I think there's two really primary implications for us to consider.
Number one, invest in face-to-face time in the presence of God.
Carve out intentional time where you can be with the Lord in his presence.
Where you can delight in who he is and what he's done for you,
and you can realize that what he has done for you demonstrates that he delights in you.
You are secure and you are delighted in.
Do this through solitude, listening prayer, lectio divino, worship music, whatever it is that works for you.
Let God reveal his presence to you.
I'm reminded of a story about an 18th century peasant who would come in every single day and sit in this rural chapel and just stare up at the front stained glass windows and the cross.
And he was just there every day, day in and day out.
And finally, the clergy member walked up to him and says, what is it that you do here every day?
And the farmer peasant said, I look at him and he looks at me and we are happy.
This is the invitation of Emmanuel, God with us.
You look at him and he looks at you and there is joy.
Invest in face-to-face time in the presence of God.
Second, we are the body of Christ.
Through the indwelling presence of the Holy Spirit, us as followers of Jesus become the incarnational presence of God to those around us who don't yet know Jesus.
Which means that we have the opportunity to extend the joy of the Lord to others through intentional face-to-face relationships.
And I'm afraid that this holiday season that claims to be all about joy has made us so busy and preoccupied that we cannot slow down and look one another in the face and be present.
And I just want to remind us that those of us who have the Holy Spirit in us carry with us the presence of God.
And that we can bring joy through face-to-face presence with individuals who are joy depleted.
Ask the Holy Spirit who he might be inviting you to invest in this holiday season.
Slow down long enough to hear a name or two and make time to bring joy, the joy of the Lord, to bring that to someone else.
Think about Moses after coming down from being in the presence of God.
It's that his face glowed.
When we spend time in the presence of God as the result that we carry the joy of God's presence to others.
Or do we immediately let whatever's happening in our world after we leave the prayer closet or the time with God just zap us of the joy that we receive from him?
What would it be like for us as followers of Jesus to spend time in the presence of God to receive joy and then go out with that joy and extend it to others?
It doesn't have to be anything ridiculous.
I've just, one practice I've been doing just since this message preparation is just like, if I'm going to go to a store to run Christmas errands, I just, I do not go if I have to be in a hurry.
I don't want to be in a store with the presence of God treating people like trash or obstacles, right?
At the best, they're just obstacles in our way of getting our list checked off.
So just, it doesn't have to be crazy or epic, just reminding yourself that you bring with you the presence of God.
And seeing people as image bearers of God who are valuable.
Seeing people as individuals, that joy is available to them through the incarnational presence of Jesus.
And you might be the person that brings that to them for the first time or the second time or whatever it might be.
Scripture says, I bring you good news that will bring great joy for all people today.
In the city of David, a savior has been born.
He will be called Emmanuel, which means God with us.
Let's pray.
Father in heaven, I thank you for yet another reminder this week that I know far less about you than I think I do.
Yet another reminder, God, that you made the human body, human brain with intention, with purpose.
God, that we are embodied human beings.
God, that our spiritual relationship with you actually impacts our physical presence.
God, may we invest in our relationship with you more intentionally.
May we receive joy through your indwelling presence.
And may we extend joy to others through face-to-face relationship.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
We're going to end by taking communion this morning.
And I wanted to really just focus on one verse.
I told you that, yeah, I'll give you guys time.
Take your time.
Don't view each other as obstacles getting to the communion cup.
No need to rush.
I told you at the beginning that this is a rabbit trail that I've been going down for a couple weeks.
Marissa's been on it for over a year.
And one of the things that she pointed out to me that just like,
like made everything, wrapped everything together in a bow.
She said, if joy really is about face-to-face presence and safe and secure relationships rooted in mutual delight,
then it really makes sense that Hebrews chapter 12 says,
For the joy set before him, he endured the cross.
That maybe, just maybe, the thing that Jesus was looking forward to most
as he went through the most brutal, excruciating, horrific death in human history,
maybe the thing that he was looking forward to the most was his reunion with the Father and the Spirit
and face-to-face presence.
That part of the incarnational presence of Jesus is that he left the joy of heaven
to walk dirty, broken, busted up, joy depleted streets.
That he spent his entire life knowing what it is to experience full joy
and seeing what we go through as broken people with depleted joy.
And that he went through the cross in order to restore everlasting joy to us.
And as he was doing so, he was looking past the cross
and seeing the Father's delight in him.
So he leaves the face-to-face presence of God
to bring us the face-to-face presence of God.
He returns to heaven and we await that glorious day
through the broken body and shed blood of Jesus
when God the Father will return to us
and we will have face-to-face presence with him around a banquet table
where there will be bread and cup
and our Father
face-to-face presence.
God is present with us at this communion table
as we take his body broken for us.
And we drink his blood shed for us.
Church, may we carry with us
out of this place the joy that we have received
in being in his presence.
It's dismissed.
Thank you.